A Guide to the Wissler Letters Collection, 1805-1881
Shenandoah County Library
Shenandoah County Library
Wissler Letters Collection, 1805-1881
Shenandoah County Library
2019-0018
1 linear foot (1 box, 63 folders)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research use.
Acquisition Information
The items in this collection were donated by Dorothy Sullenberger, Caroline Emswiler, Rosemary Wallinger, Elizabeth Tillson, who are daughters of Dorothy Page Wissler Hynes.
Rights Statements for Archival Description
The Guide to the Wissler Letters Collection is licensed under a Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International license.
Biographical/Historical Note
The items in this collection reflect the thoughts and business dealings among members of the Wissler family (John Wissler, Levi Erb, Ezra Wissler, Franklin Wissler, Christian Wissler, and Samuel B. Myers). The letters in this collection pertain to the purchase of Columbia Furnace. Samuel B. Myers (the husband of Elizabeth Wissler, the niece of John Wissler) sold the property to John Wissler. John and his family moved from Canada to Virginia. Columbia Furnace soon became a successful iron production business.
At the start of the Civil War, John Wissler and his family fled the area for Canada, due to their Republican political views. They returned after the war ended. John Wissler died in 1880, but his family continued running Columbia Furnace.
Under the Wissler family’s direction both Columbia and Liberty Furnace (which the family also owned and operated) grew until over 300 persons were employed there. They were responsible for mining ore, refining it, transporting it to rail centers, harvesting lumber to feed the furnaces, and maintaining a wide array of company structures. From this time onward the operations at the furnaces would be economic center of this area of Shenandoah County.
Unfortunately, it also led to some problems as locals clashed with individuals brought in to fill vacancies, especially when the company began to hire African Americans. In January of 1880 a race riot broke out and the owners and black workers were attacked. This two day event ended when the Wisslers agreed to hire only white workers. This eliminated a major employment source for local African Americans and forced many to emigrate or settle for lower paying service jobs.
In 1884 a group of Philadelphia businessmen purchased the furnaces and named it Columbia Liberty Iron Company. They continued both operations until 1891 when the company was sold again to H.H. Yard of Philadelphia. He closed the Columbia Furnace and built a narrow gauge railroad, nicknamed the “Dinky” to haul the ore produced and goods to the furnaces and surrounding communities.
However, making a profit proved to be difficult. Legal battles between Yard and the previous owners compounded the sites problems. In 1905 the company was again sold and reorganized as the Shenandoah Iron and Coal Company who hoped to turn a profit by modernizing operations. Their efforts proved to be unsuccessful and the furnace the closed in 1907 and the land sold to Joseph T. Jackson who used the railroad to transport lumber from the area. It closed in 1917 after the area hills had been stripped.
Scope and Content
The Wissler Letters Collection consists of 1 box of letters produced by members of the Wissler family and other Wissler family materials. The letters span the dates 1856-1881 and primarily deal with operations of the family’s iron furnaces, including several in Shenandoah County Va.
Contents List
- Box 1, Stack 9, Shelf 4 38758101567047
  - Wissler Family Genealogy, 1805-1880 (Folder 1.1)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, May 26 1856, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.2)
  - Letter, Ezra Wissler to John Wissler, June 5 1856 (Folder 1.3)
  - Letter, Samuel Myers to John Wissler, Philadelphia Pennsylvania, June 15 1856 (Folder 1.4)
  - Letter, Christian Wissler to John Wissler, June 16 1856, Lancaster County Pennsylvania (Folder 1.5)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, June 25 1856, Philadelphia Pennsylvania (Folder 1.6)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, July 1 1856, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.7)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, July 1856, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.8)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, September 15 1856, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.9)
  - Letter, Eli Phlegar to John Wissler, September 27 1856, Christiansburg Virginia (Folder 1.10)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, October 27 1856, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.11)
  - Financial Bond, Debt of Samuel Myers and others to Mark Bird, Trustee for George F. Hupp, 1857-1861 (Folder 1.12)
  - Letter, Eli Phlegar to John Wissler, February 25 1857, Christianburg Virginia (Folder 1.13)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, March 2 1857, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.14)
  - Letter, Eli Phlegar to Samuel B. Myers, March 5 1857, Christiansburg Virginia (Folder 1.15)
  - Letter, Samuel Myers to John Wissler, March 20 1857, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.16)
  - Letter, Eli Phlegar to John Wissler, March 26 1857, Christiansburg Virginia (Folder 1.17)
  - Statement of Firm S.B. Myers & Company, April 1 1857 (Folder 1.18)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, April 22 1857, Philadelphia Pennsylvania (Folder 1.19)
  - Letter, Samuel b. Myers to John Wissler, June 15 1857, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.20)
  - Letter, Eli Phlegar to Samuel B. Myers, June 29 1857, Christiansburg Virginia (Folder 1.21)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, July 10 1857, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.22)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, August 11 1857, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.23)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, August 11 1857, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.24)
  - Letter, Sem Wissler to John Wissler, November 1 1857, Salem (Folder 1.25)
  - Letter, Sem Wissler to John Wissler, November 30 1857, Salem (Folder 1.26)
  - Letter, Sem Wissler to John Wissler, November 30 1857, Salem (Folder 1.27)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wisser, February 14 1858, Orkney Springs Virginia (Folder 1.28)
  - License, John Wissler & Company to Operate Store, April 12 1858, Shenandoah County Virginia (Folder 1.29)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, June 8 1859, Henrietta Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.30)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, March 19 1860, Henrietta Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.31)
  - Letter, Samuel B. Myers to John Wissler, April 1860, Union Forge Virginia (Folder 1.32)
  - Letter, William R. Perfater to “Messrs Wissler &Myers,” April 27 1860, Blacksburg Virginia (Folder 1.33)
  - Letter, Christian Wissler to John Wissler, July 2 1860 (Folder 1.34)
  - Letter, Christian Wissler to John Wissler, Juuly 18 1860 (Folder 1.35)
  - Letter, Rob P. Fail to John Wissler, August 27 1860, Glencoe Canada (Folder 1.36)
  - Letter, Christian Wissler to John Wissler, January 25 1861 (Folder 1.37)
  - Contract for “Hammered Iron” between John Wissler & Company and G.S.P. Triplett, January 1 1862, Warrenton Virginia (Folder 1.38)
  - Letter, “Wheat and Brothers” to John Wissler and Company, Alexandria Virginia, May 28, 1862 (Folder 1.39)
  - Letter, James G. Fravel to George Rye US Navy Department, December 15 1864, Woodstock Virginia (Folder 1.40)
  - Letter, Levi Erb to Franklin Wissler, February 24 1867 (Folder 1.41)
  - Letter, Franklin H. Wissler to Levi Erb and Mary Heiser Wissler Erb, March 12 1867 (Folder 1.42)
  - Letter, Franklin H. Wissler to Levi Erb, April 9 1867, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.43)
  - Letter, J. Wissler to “Mother & Sons & Daughters,” Mt. Torry Furnace Virginia, April 12, 1868 (Folder 1.44)
  - Letter, Ezra Wissler to Franklin H. Wissler, April 16 1868, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.45)
  - Letter, Ezra Wissler to Levi Erb, June 19 1868, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.46)
  - Letter, Ezra Wissler to Levi Erb, August 31 1868, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.47)
  - Letter, J.E. Wissler to Levi Erb, November 6 1868, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.48)
  - Loan Promissory Note, Franklin Wissler to Levi Erb, $5000, January 1 1870, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.49)
  - Letter, J.R. Wissler to Levi Erb, March 18 1870, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.50)
  - Letter, Ezra Wissler to Levi Erb, July 5 1870, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.51)
  - Letter, J.R. Wissler to Levi Erb, July 30 1871, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.52)
  - Letter, J.R. Wissler to Levi Erb, September 11 1871, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.53)
  - Letter, J.R. Wissler to Levi Erb, October 24 1871, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.54)
  - Letter, J.R. Wissler to Levi Erb, November 26 1871, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.55)
  - Letter, “J & E Wissler” to Levi Erb, December 11 1871, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.56)
  - Letter, Thomas E. Auld to Levi Erb, April 14 1872, Martinsburg West Virginia (Folder 1.57)
  - Letter, “J & E Wissler” to Levi Erb, June 10 1872, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.58)
  - Financial Sheet, Payments by “J & E Wissler,” 1875-1876 (Folder 1.59)
  - Letter, Ezra Wissler to Levi Erb, March 31 1876, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.60)
  - Letter, “J & E Wissler” to Levi Erb, July 6 1876, Salem Ontario (Folder 1.61)
  - Letter, R.W. Stone to Levi Erb, June 27 1881, Columbia Furnace Virginia (Folder 1.62)
  - Letter Fragment, Signed Samuel B. Myers, Undated (Folder 1.63)